<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title></title>
    <link>https://esnielsen.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content on </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 15 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Representation: The foundation of conservation</title>
      <link>https://esnielsen.github.io/project/respresentation/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Sep 2018 16:32:54 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://esnielsen.github.io/project/respresentation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Designing Marine Protected Areas, or MPAS, can be difficult, and we still have a lot to learn - as beautifully portrayed in the comic above by &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ohdakuwaqa.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Anju Sabu&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are complex and dynamic social-ecological systems that need to be weighed and balanced to create an arrangement of MPAs that best protect the natural environment, and provide for various cultural and economic uses of marine resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, we have come a long way in understanding how to best create this balance, often using spatial planning concepts, which this video by &lt;a href=&#34;https://jenmcgowanresearch.wordpress.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Jennifer McGowan&lt;/a&gt; does a superb job at explaining:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/1IDeKJJO7s8&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;However, as scientists, we often like to take simple concepts like targeting representation in MPAs, and make it more complex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is described in an Epistle by the conservation planning guru &lt;a href=&#34;http://possinghamlab.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Prof Hugh Possingham&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;__&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;The Lame-duck Conservation Principle&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember the good old days when conservation planning was just two main principles – adequacy and representation?  It seems so simple and logical. But at some point we lost sight of the importance of representation, the simple notion of protecting a sample of everything in a well-managed protected area. What happened?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In theory, representation is still at the top of the international conservation agenda, it gets a solid mention in Aichi Target 11, which states:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;By 2020, at least 17 percent of terrestrial and inland water areas and 10 percent of coastal and marine areas, especially areas of particular importance for biodiversity and ecosystem services, are conserved through effectively and equitably managed, ecologically representative and well-connected systems of protected areas and other effective area-based conservation measures, and integrated into the wider landscape and seascape.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Nature Conservancy has championed the cause of representation, with representation and resilience forming the core principles of our new protect land and water strategy. But the rest of the world seems to have lost interest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my simple mind, The Nature Conservancy is the &amp;lsquo;habitat organisation.&amp;rsquo; That is why I joined.  We focus on how to make more quality habitat, in all its forms, because it delivers benefits for people and nature.  So it is only logical that we always return to a strong focus on habitat representation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet while we continue to keep our eye on the ball, some organisations and groups believe that a focus on threatened species, via Key Biodiversity Areas, is the best way to prioritisation protection.  Others are pushing connectivity as the most important conservation principle — let’s connect the Yukon to Yellowstone.  I agree that both are important, but still very much secondary to the notion of protecting a representative sample of habitats or ecosystems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why are we losing this marketing campaign?  In my opinion, representation is on the backburner because it is intellectually a little dull.  Connectivity captures the imagination of many scientists, it can be measured by 100 different metrics, while ideas like &amp;lsquo;corridors&amp;rsquo; seem to capture the hearts and minds of the public and politicians.  I love connectivity, but I am convinced it is a secondary issue. And, of course, threatened species are all so sexy — with their big brown eyes— much sexier than a place like the mallee woodland (my favourite habitat in Australia).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So here’s my challenge to you:  Representation is the most boring but important concept in conservation. So how to we make it sexy again?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;__&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been thinking of Prof Possingham&amp;rsquo;s question of how do we make the simple act of targeting representation sexy - and I think the answer comes down to making representation a surrogate for adaptability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would argue that nothing is sexier in conservation science at the moment than prioritising areas that are more resilient to climate change. My work specifically looks at areas that are more genetically diverse, and thus assumed to be more resilient to environmental change. And interestingly, there have been several recent publications that suggest that by representing different habitat types (or different species distributions), you are also capturing genetic diversity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can find such papers in the links below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/pdf/10.1111/ddi.12195&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Geographical surrogates of genetic variation for selecting island populations for conservation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.pnas.org/content/pnas/114/48/12755.full.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Environmental and geographic variables are effective surrogates for genetic variation in conservation planning&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/pdf/10.1111/j.1472-4642.2011.00752.x&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Incorporating evolutionary processes into conservation planning using species distribution data: a case study with the western Mediterranean herpetofauna: Evolutionary processes in conservation planning&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/pdf/10.1111/ddi.12113&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Testing large-scale conservation corridors designed for patterns and processes: comparative phylogeography of three tree species&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And of coarse, this is science, so here is this paper arguing the opposite:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1111/j.1365-294X.2008.04039.x&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;On the validity of habitat as a predictor of genetic structure in aquatic systems: a comparative study using California water beetles&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the argument of representative habitats as surrogates of species and genetic diversity could help bring this elegant practice back in the forefront of conservation planning, but I think it will also require scientists to change our perspective of our work, as to not think about how well our work will publish, but how well it can be applied to &amp;lsquo;real-world&amp;rsquo; conservation practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So really we need a whole paradigm shift within Academia&amp;hellip; but for now let&amp;rsquo;s just settle with a haiku about representation in conservation planning:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;~&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MPA designs,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To make easier target:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Representation&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;~&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Women in STEM</title>
      <link>https://esnielsen.github.io/project/women-in-stem/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Sep 2018 16:32:54 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://esnielsen.github.io/project/women-in-stem/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have always loved Cindi Lauper&amp;rsquo;s style and her iconic song, &amp;lsquo;Girls just want to have fun&amp;rsquo;, and when I saw this photo (see above) from the Women&amp;rsquo;s March, I knew I needed to make my own rendition of the song. I hope you enjoy!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/W7aTK0xpJwQ&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I originally learned how to play the song on the ukulele following &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=xJBNyWMbZEE&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;this tutorial&lt;/a&gt;. The lyrics and tabs below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;__&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Women in STEM&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[F] When you ask some girls, what’s a cool career
[Dm] They say being an ecologist or an engineer
[Bb] Or maybe in psychology or neuroscience,
[Dm] Some girls, [C*] just want to do [Bb] science,
[Dm] Some girls [C] just want to be [F] scientists,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[F] I know there’s still discrimination
[Dm] But don’t let it stop you from a career in STEM
[Bb] Follow your dreams is what I urge
[Dm] Some girls [C*] just want to do [Bb] research,
[Dm] So we’re going to [C] pursue [F] research&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[F] Ya that&amp;rsquo;s all we really want
[Dm] Some funding
[F] To run experiments
[Dm] And make [C*] infer- [Bb] ences
[Dm] Ya to [C] help [F] society&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[F] Make a lab with lots of diversity
[Dm] Including women and minorities
[Bb] You don’t have to look far, you don&amp;rsquo;t have to search
[Dm] And it will make [C*] for better [Bb] research,
[Dm] Ya and makes for [C] better [F] researchers&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[F] Ya that&amp;rsquo;s all we really want
[Dm] Some funding
[F] To run experiments
[Dm] And make [C*] infer- [Bb] ences
[Dm] Ya to [C] help [F] society&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;__&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to hear more about diversity and women in STEM you can:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;watch this &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=mPohBFk6SV0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;TED talk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;read &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-018-05316-5&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;this article&lt;/a&gt; on diversity in academia&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;listen to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.npr.org/2019/01/24/687707404/creative-differences-the-benefits-of-reaching-out-to-people-unlike-ourselves&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;this podcast&lt;/a&gt; which highlights how diversity in academia leads to heightened creativity&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;read &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.org/en-us/explore/magazine/magazine-articles/interview-robyn-james/?src=social.nature.facebook.mag&amp;amp;utm_campaign=social&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;this article&lt;/a&gt; on women in conservation!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pool-seq Programs for Population Genomics</title>
      <link>https://esnielsen.github.io/post/a-guide-to-ngs-pool-seq-programs/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://esnielsen.github.io/post/a-guide-to-ngs-pool-seq-programs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As Pooled sequencing gains popularity in the world of genomics, more and more programs are being introduced to specifically handle Pool-seq data. However, for students such as myself, it can be difficult to find the right program for each step of the bioinformatics process, and to know the correct data format and parameters used with each individual program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a short recap of the Pool-seq bioinformatic programs that I have gathered, including input and output files, and any additional notes I had on the program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;~&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://sourceforge.net/p/popoolation/wiki/Manual/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Popoolation&lt;/a&gt; -&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;input: a samtools pileup file (Note: must be made by samtools version 0.1.18 and below, and cannot take mpileup files)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;output: a pool-specific sync file, from which population specific diversity indices (such at Tajima&amp;rsquo;s pi &amp;amp; D, Watterson&amp;rsquo;s theta) can be calculated with the Variance-sliding.pl&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://sourceforge.net/p/popoolation2/wiki/Manual/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Popoolation2&lt;/a&gt; -&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;input: a samtools mpileup file (Note: must be made by samtools version 0.1.18 and below)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;output: a sync file including multiple pools, from which diversity metrics (FSTs) can be calculated. The sync file can also be converted into a genepop file for further analysis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notes of Popoolation/Polpoolation2:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sync2GenePop conversion step requires custom scripts to be written so that it can be run on all loci at once, instead of each locus individually. Feel free to contact me if you wish to see perl scripts used to create a GenePop file for an entire pool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ekg/freebayes&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;FreeBayes&lt;/a&gt; -&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;input: BAM files &amp;amp; a reference fasta file&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;output: a pool VCF file&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/vibansal/crisp&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;CRISP&lt;/a&gt; -&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;input: BAM files, pool sample sizes, reference fasta file (NB: requires at least 2 pools/2 BAM files)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;output: a pool VCF file&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://snver.sourceforge.net/manual.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;SNVer&lt;/a&gt; -&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;input: BAM files &amp;amp; a text file with the BAM file names, number of haploids, number of samples, and filtering thresholds&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;output: a pool VCF file&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notes on FreeBayes, CRISP &amp;amp; SNVer:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though these programs make VCF files, I personally could not find a way to convert these VCF files to other formats such as genepop/genind/genlight with conversion tools such as PGDspider, vcf2genepop, or genomic_converter. However, it seems like it can be input into the R package &lt;a href=&#34;https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/poolfstat/poolfstat.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;poolfstat&lt;/a&gt; to calculate F-statistics, and be converted into files for BayPass and SelEstim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/EmanueleRaineri/snape-pooled&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;SNAPE-pool&lt;/a&gt; -&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;input: a samtools pileup file (not mpileup)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;output: allele frequency output files&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/lucaferretti/npstat&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;npstat&lt;/a&gt; -&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;input: a samtools mpileup file + individual BAM files (per pool). Can also take GFF3 annotations to perform McDonald-Krietman tests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;output: population specific diversity indices (such at Tajima&amp;rsquo;s pi &amp;amp; D, Watterson&amp;rsquo;s theta), and population differentiation (FSTs)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/chasewnelson/SNPGenie&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;SNPgenie&lt;/a&gt; -&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;input: a VCF file (for a single pool), a reference fasta file, and GTF annotation file&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;output: πN/πS, dN/dS, and other evolutionary parameters (has a great number output files)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note: This program is only for model species with annotated genomes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/bcm-uga/pcadapt&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;PCAdapt&lt;/a&gt; -&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;input:  a frequency matrix with n rows and L columns (where n is the number of populations and L is the number of genetic markers)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;output: several plots and list of potential outlier loci&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note: For my data, this program suggested quite a large number of putative outliers, especially compared to Bayescan, Loistan, and Popoolation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www1.montpellier.inra.fr/CBGP/software/selestim/files/SelEstim_1.1.7_manual.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;SelEstim&lt;/a&gt; -&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;input: an allele/read count file&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ouput: a &amp;lsquo;delta&amp;rsquo; output file which is input in R to identify outlier loci&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note: I personally tried SelEstim with ~ 8,000 loci, and the program ran for about 4 weeks without finishing, so could not use due to time restraints.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/magicDGS/PoolHMM/blob/master/README.txt&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Pool-hmm&lt;/a&gt; -&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;input: a samtools mpileup (Note: the mpileup command should not have -u or -g option)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;output: allele frequency spectrum, plus probability of &amp;ldquo;Neutral&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;Intermediate&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Selection&amp;rdquo; for each polymorphic site, with additional stats files&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;~&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, here is a short list of some pipelines available for Pool-seq &amp;amp; non-model organisms:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/StevenMicheletti/poolparty&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Pool-party&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/jpuritz/dDocent&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;dDocent&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://software.broadinstitute.org/gatk/documentation/tooldocs/3.8-0/org_broadinstitute_gatk_tools_walkers_haplotypecaller_HaplotypeCaller.php&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;GATK&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://catchenlab.life.illinois.edu/stacks/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;STACKS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, for complete bioinformatics beginners, &lt;a href=&#34;https://usegalaxy.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Galaxy&lt;/a&gt; is a great way to understand various bioinformatic programs and their command lines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;~&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy analysing!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Privacy Policy</title>
      <link>https://esnielsen.github.io/privacy/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://esnielsen.github.io/privacy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Complex signatures of genomic variation of two non-model marine species in a homogeneous environment</title>
      <link>https://esnielsen.github.io/publication/person-re-identification/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 May 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://esnielsen.github.io/publication/person-re-identification/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Example Talk</title>
      <link>https://esnielsen.github.io/talk/example-talk/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://esnielsen.github.io/talk/example-talk/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Embed your slides or video here using &lt;a href=&#34;https://sourcethemes.com/academic/post/writing-markdown-latex/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;shortcodes&lt;/a&gt;. Further details can easily be added using &lt;em&gt;Markdown&lt;/em&gt; and $\rm \LaTeX$ math code.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Multispecies genetic objectives in spatial conservation planning</title>
      <link>https://esnielsen.github.io/publication/clothing-search/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://esnielsen.github.io/publication/clothing-search/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
