<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on </title>
    <link>/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Get Genetic With It</title>
      <link>/post/a-guide-to-ngs-pool-seq-programs/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/a-guide-to-ngs-pool-seq-programs/</guid>
      <description>Here is my entry to the Evolution Film Contest.
Every year our university opens its doors to high school students, so that they can get an idea of what postgraduates do within each lab. My intention with this video is to open our lab doors to a much wider audience and offer a view into my world as a PhD student studying molecular ecology. I wanted to make a video that is not only fun to watch, but also describes the basic theories and methodologies used within molecular ecology.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pool-seq Programs for Population Genomics</title>
      <link>/post/a-guide-to-ngs-pool-seq-programs/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/a-guide-to-ngs-pool-seq-programs/</guid>
      <description>As Pooled sequencing gains popularity in the world of genomics, more and more programs are being introduced to specifically handle Pool-seq data. However, for students such as myself, it can be difficult to find the right program for each step of the bioinformatics process, and to know the correct data format and parameters used with each individual program.
Here is a short recap of the Pool-seq bioinformatic programs that I have gathered, including input and output files, and any additional notes I had on the program.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>