<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects on </title>
    <link>https://esnielsen.github.io/project/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Projects on </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 03 Aug 2021 16:32:54 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://esnielsen.github.io/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>GeeklyEDU Biology Videos</title>
      <link>https://esnielsen.github.io/project/geeklyedu/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Aug 2021 16:32:54 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://esnielsen.github.io/project/geeklyedu/</guid>
      <description>In the time between completing my PhD and starting my postdoc, I was doing some freelance science communication work (which I found on the UpWork site for anyone interesting in freelance work).
One of the jobs I had was creating ~5 minute videos explaining biology topics at the first-year university level. To see some of my work, click on the links below!
                                            </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>IMCC6 Talk</title>
      <link>https://esnielsen.github.io/project/imcc6.talk/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 Aug 2020 16:32:54 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://esnielsen.github.io/project/imcc6.talk/</guid>
      <description>Below is my oral presentation at the 2020 International Marine Conservation Congress, in which I condense my PhD into a ten minute talk (which is a great science communication exercise!).
This was my first online conference, which I really enjoyed because if you missed anything you could watch it later, asking questions wasn&amp;rsquo;t as intimidating as in person, and talks were spread out over two weeks which made the whole experience less draining than an in person conference!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>TalkClimate2Me questions</title>
      <link>https://esnielsen.github.io/project/climate.convos/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Apr 2020 16:32:54 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://esnielsen.github.io/project/climate.convos/</guid>
      <description>During the COVID-19 pandemic, I have spent a lot of time trying to reflect and reconnect. Many of us are having conversations with those we haven&amp;rsquo;t spoken to in a while, and discussing topics we normally wouldn&amp;rsquo;t.
As a self-proclaimed &amp;lsquo;Climate Change Person&amp;rsquo;, I am often looking to have conversations with regards to what I believe is the greatest threat our species and planet are facing (aka the climate crisis/6th mass extinction/human-induced snowballing interactions of doom).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My Dance Your PhD Entry!</title>
      <link>https://esnielsen.github.io/project/dance-your-phd-entry/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Feb 2020 16:32:54 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://esnielsen.github.io/project/dance-your-phd-entry/</guid>
      <description>Below is my entry for the 2020 &amp;lsquo;Dance Your PhD&amp;rsquo; video contest created by Gonzo Labs and Science Magazine.
With this video I aimed to describe a chapter of my PhD via dance, but also hoped to achieve the following:
 make concepts of population genetics accessible to those with little previous knowledge on the subject
 engage and collaborate with local dance groups to conduct knowledge transfer between the sciences and the arts</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2019 Conservation Symposium Review</title>
      <link>https://esnielsen.github.io/project/sccp_2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Dec 2019 16:32:54 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://esnielsen.github.io/project/sccp_2019/</guid>
      <description>On Nov 4-7th 2019 I had the opportunity to attend The Conservation Symposium, which aims to bring together those working on conservation issues within South Africa.
I enjoy this conference because it takes me out of my academia bubble and transports me into the ‘on the ground’ conservation practice realm. Students and academics make up a small portion of the attendees, outnumbered by NGOs, consulting companies, government organizations, attorneys, reporters, and filmmakers.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Youth 4 Conservation</title>
      <link>https://esnielsen.github.io/project/youth4cons/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Sep 2019 16:32:54 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://esnielsen.github.io/project/youth4cons/</guid>
      <description>Below is my entry to the Youth4Conservation video contest for the 2019 South African Conservation Symposium.
The Youth4Conservation movement partners young volunteers with local conservation organisations to help tackle critical conservation issues within South Africa.
This year, the Conservation Symposium partnered with WildTrust, offering discounted registration prices to young attendees who send a short video describing how they are contributing to conservation within South Africa.
With this video, I hope to share why genetics and genomics are important to conserving biodiversity, especially with regards to an uncertain climatic future.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2019 WIOMSA Symposium Review</title>
      <link>https://esnielsen.github.io/project/wiomsa/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Dec 2018 16:32:54 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://esnielsen.github.io/project/wiomsa/</guid>
      <description>During July 1-5 2019, I attended the 11th Western Indian Ocean Marine Science Association (WIOMSA) symposium at the University of Mauritius with two of my colleagues Nikki and Molly.
WIOMSA is always a great conference as it covers a variety of scientific disciplines and has a strong focus on integrating research and management within the region. Some of the highlights were:
 Prof Golden’s plenary which discussed the impacts of climate change on small-scale fisheries and human nutrition.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Get Genetic With It</title>
      <link>https://esnielsen.github.io/project/getgenetic/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Dec 2018 16:32:54 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://esnielsen.github.io/project/getgenetic/</guid>
      <description>Below is my entry to the Evolution Film Contest.
_
Every year our university opens its doors to high school students, so that they can get an idea of what postgraduates do within each lab. My intention with this video is to open our lab doors to a much wider audience and offer a view into my world as a PhD student studying conservation genetics. I wanted to make a video that is not only fun to watch, but also describes the basic theories and methodologies used within molecular ecology.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Sustainable Future</title>
      <link>https://esnielsen.github.io/project/sustainability/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Sep 2018 16:32:54 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://esnielsen.github.io/project/sustainability/</guid>
      <description>The Earth is changing, and rapidly. In the midst of a global pandemic, 2020 tied with 2016 as the warmest year ON RECORD. Ultimately, in order to reduce emissions by 45% by 2030, we will need large corporations and governments to take the lead to ensure that ongoing global development shifts from fossil fuels to renewable energy.
But while it is mainly a handful of companies that are responsible for 71% of greenhouse gas emissions, we as individuals and consumers can also fight towards and create a more sustainable future.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Representation</title>
      <link>https://esnielsen.github.io/project/respresentation/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Sep 2018 16:32:54 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://esnielsen.github.io/project/respresentation/</guid>
      <description>Designing Marine Protected Areas, or MPAS, can be difficult, and we still have a lot to learn - as beautifully portrayed in the comic above by Anju Sabu.
There are complex and dynamic social-ecological systems that need to be weighed and balanced to create an arrangement of MPAs that best protect the natural environment, and provide for various cultural and economic uses of marine resources.
But, we have come a long way in understanding how to best create this balance, often using spatial planning concepts, which this video by Jennifer McGowan does a superb job at explaining:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Women in STEM</title>
      <link>https://esnielsen.github.io/project/women-in-stem/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Sep 2018 16:32:54 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://esnielsen.github.io/project/women-in-stem/</guid>
      <description>I have always loved Cindi Lauper&amp;rsquo;s style and her iconic song, &amp;lsquo;Girls just want to have fun&amp;rsquo;, and when I saw this photo (see above) from the Women&amp;rsquo;s March, I knew I needed to make my own rendition of the song. I hope you enjoy!
  I originally learned how to play the song on the ukulele following this tutorial. The lyrics and tabs below:
__
Women in STEM</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>